[Music introduction]
Καλησπέρα, Αθήνα. こんにちは、アテネの皆さん。
本日は、お招きいただきありがとうございます。
ディスラプトが必要なんですか？私は持ってますよ。
いや、私が持ってるのは正真正銘の革命です。
これからお話しするのは最もエキサイティングで興味深く
そしておそらくもっとも重要なテクノロジー革新・・・
ここ20年の間のコンピューターサイエンスの分野における
最も価値のある発明です。
今日はビットコインの事をお話しに来ました。
皆さんもおそらく以前に聞いた事があると思います。
簡単なチェックをしてみましょう。
今日より前からビットコインについて耳にした事がある方は何人いますか？
わかりました。いい集まりですね。
ではビットコインを保有しているという人は？ますますいい感じ。
ビットコインはデジタル・マネーです。
ですが、それ以上のものです。
ビットコインをデジタル・マネーと言うのは
インターネットを大げさな電話とか電子メールが全てと言うようなものです。
マネーは最初のアプリケーションに過ぎません。
ビットコインはテクノロジーであり、通貨であり国際的なペイメント・ネットワークです。
そして分散化されています。銀行や政府に依りません。
人類の歴史上、今までこんな事はなしえなかったんです。
この発明は本当に革命的なものです。振り返ってみれば、これが歴史的な瞬間だったことがわかるでしょう。
コンピュータ・サイエンスの進化のみならず社会政治的な革命が起きているんです。
では、始めましょう。ビットコインはデジタル・マネーです。
ユーロやドルもまたデジタルです。しかし、ビットコインは政府によって所有されていません。
世界中のどこからでも送る事ができます。
瞬時に、安全に、そして最小限の料金で。
2日前、ビットコインネットワーク上で過去最大のトランザクションが記録されました。
誰かが1億5000万ドル[相当のビットコイン]を[約10分で]手数料0円で送金したのです。
これでビットコインが、国際的な決済システムの面で、いかに破壊的なイノベーションになるかを把握できるはずです。
ですが、これは単なる始まりに過ぎません。
ビットコインは2008年にサトシ・ナカモトと呼ばれる人物によって考案されたデジタル通貨です。
彼は論文を発表し、そこで分散型ネットワークを作る方法を発見したと述べました。
そのネットワークは、いかなる中央管理権限もなしにコンセンサス／合意に達する事が可能であると言います。
もしコンピューター・サイエンスや分散型システムを学んだ事があれば、これはビザンチン将軍問題として知られています。
この問題は[1982年]に最初に記述されました。
2008年まで、これは未解決な問題でした。
しかし、この問題を解決することの重要性は理解されていました。
そしてサトシ・ナカモトはそれを解いたというのです。
次に何が起こったと思いますか？みんな彼を笑いました。
大勢が彼を無視し、相手にしませんでした。
彼は論文を発表しました。そして3カ月後、彼はビットコインネットワークを開始するソフトウェアを発表しました。
ビットコインは会社でも組織でもありません。
ビットコインはちょうどインターネットのTCP/IPのような標準プロトコルです。
誰によっても所有されていません。
数学的なルールに基づいて運用されます。
ネットワークに参加する人は全員、それに合意しなければなりません。
ビットコインは、このコンセンサスの仕組みを介して、ネットワーク上でどのような取引が発生したか、現在誰がどのようなお金を所有しているかについて合意するコンピュータの分散型ネットワークです。
もし私が、電子メールを送るみたいに
お金を他の誰かの“口座”にピア・ツー・ピアネットワークで送ったなら
間に仲介者は誰もいません。
私のコンピューターから受信者のコンピューターへと何の介入もなしに。[ビットコインのトランザクションはブロードキャストされます。]
10分毎に、ネットワークはどんなトランザクションが生じたかの合意に達します。
いかなる中央集権的な権限もなしに、ある意味電子的に行われる選挙によってです。
この特定の[ビザンチン将軍問題への]解決策は、通貨よりももっともっと重要です。
通貨は、分散型コンセンサスシステム上に構築できる最初のアプリにすぎません。
他の用途として、投票、株式所有権、資産登録、公証、その他多くのアプリがあります。
以前には考えた事もなかったアプリケーション。
私が初めてビットコインを発見したのは2011年の事です。
[初期の時代の]インターネット以来
自分が見た可能性にここまで完全に圧倒されるような感覚は、今まで感じたことがありません。
私も1991年の商用化前だったインターネットの夜明けの時代にいました。
私にはこれが世界を変えるテクノロジデーであることがわかりました。
周りにいる皆にそう言って歩きましたが、誰も私の言うことを信じませんでした。
それと全く同じ感覚をビットコインに感じています。
皆さんの何人かはビットコインは通貨だと聞いたことがあると思います。
お金のシステムとして、現在、値段はある時はむやみやたらに高かったり次の日には安かったりしています。
私が皆さんにこの場で言いたいのは、値段は無視してくださいということ。お金としてのビットコインの値段は無視して、テクノロジーとしてのビットコインと
ビットコインが作り上げるネットワークを理解してくださいということ。
もしお金でしくじってしまったのなら、単に別の通貨をまた立ち上げればいいのです。
ビットコインのテクノロジーは、もう発明されなかったことにはできません。このテクノロジーは、この惑星で見たことのないスケールの分散型組織の可能性を作り出します。
これがビットコインが私にとってなぜ重要なのか、その理由です。
今日の世界では、およそ10億人の人々が銀行口座を持ち、
主に上流階級や西欧諸国の中で、クレジットへのアクセスや国際金融を扱う能力を有しています。
この地球上の6億5000万人の人々は、銀行の世界へのコネクションが何もありません。
彼らは他のあらゆる国政資源へのアクセスがほとんどないキャッシュベースの社会で暮らしています。
But they don't need banks. Two billion people are already
on the internet; with a simple application download,
they can become participants in an international
economy, using an international currency that...
can be transmitted anywhere with [little
or] no fees, and no government controls.
They can connect to a world of international,
peer-to-peer finance. Bitcoin is the money of the people.
[It operates according to] mathematical rules
that everyone agrees on. No [centralized] control.
Bring six and a half billion people into productive society,
connecting them to the rest of the world,
is truly revolutionary.
First, we will start by affecting the payment processors,
these enormous companies that make it...
more expensive to send money
the poorer the destination country is.
This situation is exploitative and corrupt.
These organizations profit enormously for a function
that can be done in bitcoin for [little or no fee].
As an adage of the internet once went, I just replaced
your entire industry with a hundred lines of Python.
That is exactly what we will do with Bitcoin.
How can you use bitcoin today? Simply
speaking, bitcoin can operate as a currency.
You can think of it as buying a foreign currency.
You can connect to an exchange over the web,
wire some euros, and use them to buy bitcoin...
at the current exchange rate.
But that is not really the right way to do it.
We are entrepreneurs, right? We want to disrupt.
The best way [to obtain bitcoin] is by
finding a product or service you can offer...
that someone with bitcoin would want to buy.
Start by earning bitcoin.
If you want to start a business, there are
two barriers to becoming a global business.
The first barrier: it is difficult to transport
products and services across borders.
With the internet, we solved that. We can now create
products and services to sell that are virtual.
We could sell and deliver anywhere in the
world, but we still had one big problem.
How do we get paid?
Bitcoin solves that part.
It allows us to receive payments from
anywhere in the world, near instantaneously.
The Bitcoin network allows any individual to send
an amount as small one hundred millionth of a bitcoin,
which in today's terms is
a very tiny amount of money.
You can't do that with traditional
money and payment systems.
Credit cards were made in the 1950s,
certainly not made for an internet age.
Bitcoin is made for the internet age.
If you can send payments that are one hundredth
or thousandth of a euro, you can sell content...
with microtransactions.
You can collect tiny payments from millions of people
and then aggregate them to be worth something.
On the same network where you can send one
thousandth of a euro, you can send one billion euros.
The fee could be exactly the same, because
it depends on the size of the transaction in kilobytes,
not the [value of the money].
Let's look back at the internet, the lessons
we learned, and why bitcoin is important.
One of the most important principles
on the internet is neutrality.
The internet doesn't distinguish between
large organizations and small organizations.
It doesn't know the difference
between CNN and an Egyptian blogger.
It provides the opportunity for a blogger to speak to
the world with the same power of voice that CNN has.
Bitcoin is neutral to sender and recipient,
as well as to the value of a transaction.
That means every citizen and user of
Bitcoin has the ability to innovate in finance.
Instruments, payment systems, and currency,
with the same facilities that a bank has.
You can become Citibank.
That is truly revolutionary.
It [transforms] a hierarchical system of international
finance that achieved security by limiting access.
That is the method of "trust" on our payment systems.
You can't get in unless you are vetted.
Bitcoin turns that on its head, with a flat and
decentralized network where every node is equal.
The protocol is neutral to the transactions
and pushes innovation to the edge of the network.
This creates the same phenomenon we saw
on the internet: innovation without permission.
You don't need to ask anyone for your
application to be published on the internet.
You don't need to ask anyone to completely subvert
a new industry with your information technology.
On Bitcoin, you don't need to ask anyone to invent a
new financial instrument, payment system, or service.
You can just do it. You can just write the code.
You are now part of an international financial network.
You can run that code and come
in contact with millions of consumers.
Now, it is still early days. We don't yet have
the polished interfaces. It is difficult to use.
[The media says] it is used by criminals,
but it is not easy to see who is using bitcoin.
I have heard all of those [accusations] before.
When I was on the internet in 1991, it was "a den
of thieves," pornographers, pirates, and criminals.
But it didn't matter and it doesn't matter now,
because the same power of the technology,
used by a criminal to promote their criminal activities,
can be used by all the rest of us to do good,
to do incredible things all across the world.
There are more of us. Bitcoin creates an environment
that is ripe for innovation. It is not just a currency.
It is a technology, a network, and a currency.
I can tell you, I am very happy that bitcoin's price is
climbing. I own some bitcoins, and it feels kind of nice.
But I don't care about the price.
If Bitcoin crashed tomorrow morning,
the technology is still revolutionary.
If a website or application fails,
the internet doesn't go away.
If you understand that Bitcoin is a technology, not just
a currency, you can truly grasp its the importance.
Again, it is not just about us.
It is about the other six billion.
It is about bringing financial integration
that the world has never seen before.
From our perspective, it is a great technology
we can use for disruptive Innovation.
We can build some interesting services.
If you are a Kenyan farmer raising money to buy seeds,
you can join in decentralized, peer-to-peer lending,
and reach out to lenders all across the globe.
This is not just a technology, it is life-changing.
The impact Bitcoin will have on the vast majority of the
world which lives under repressive and corrupt regimes,
with central banks that impose
hyperinflation of 30% or more per month.
It is more important to see how
Bitcoin can affect all of those people.
There are two billion people on the internet;
only one billion of them have bank accounts.
We can change that. It will not be easy.
Make no mistake about it, when you
[introduce] a disruptive technology into...
the middle of the most powerful organizations
[and governments] on the planet, they won't like it.
Right now, we are still in the early stages.
To use a trite expression, "First they ignore us, then
they laugh at us, then they fight us, and then we win."
We are still at the laughing stage,
and that is quite all right.
By the time they start fighting us, they will have
already lost. This technology will be global.
More than $2.5 billion dollars has come from Chinese
investors who discovered a counterbalance...
to world domination by the global
reserve currency of the U.S. dollar.
There are about 180 currencies in the world,
but there is only one international currency.
There are about 180 currencies controlled by central
banks and governments, but only one is mathematical.
That is bitcoin. We will build more of them.
Cryptographic currencies will be
a mainstay of our financial future.
They will be part of the future of this planet.
They [can't be] uninvented, and it is as simple as that.
You cannot turn that omelet back into eggs.
There are already have more than
a hundred competing currencies.
This shows how quickly innovation has
exploded beyond bitcoin the currency.
There are many alternative coins, altcoins as
they're known, that use the same basic technology:
a decentralized consensus network and an asset ledger.
There [can be] other forms of currency that are
inflationary or deflationary, that use demurrage...
or negative interest rates.
Currencies that redistribute a proportion
of the income to charitable organisations.
We can invent new forms of
money and financial instruments.
Bitcoin is programmable money.
Once you have programmable money,
the possibilities are truly endless.
Many of the basic concepts in our current
system depend on legal contracts.
We can convert them into algorithmic contracts
that can be enforced on the Bitcoin network.
As I said before, there is no counterparty. If I choose to
send value to another part of the peer-to-peer network.
no one is in between.
if I invent a new form of money, I can deploy it
to the entire world and invite others to join me.
If you see that Bitcoin has the [potential]
to not only introduce money for the internet...
Because it is the perfect money for
the internet: instant, safe, and free.
Yes, it is money for the internet, but it is also
so much more. Bitcoin is the internet of money.
Currency is only the first application. If you grasp that,
you can look beyond the fad and the price volatility.
At its core, it is a revolutionary technology that will
change the world forever. Join me in this revolution.
ありがとうございました。[拍手]